<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Remonstrance of the suffering people called Quakers clearing their innocency from the many false aspersions, slanders and suggestions, which are lately come abroad in the nation causlesly [sic] upon them.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1665</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 34 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A56996</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1016</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R4321</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11792068</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11792068</idno>
            <idno type="VID">49253</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A56996)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 49253)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 821:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Remonstrance of the suffering people called Quakers clearing their innocency from the many false aspersions, slanders and suggestions, which are lately come abroad in the nation causlesly [sic] upon them.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1665.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Persecutions.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:49253:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49253:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Remonſtrance OF THE Suffering-PEOPLE of GOD, CALLED QUAKERS: Clearing their Innocency from the many falſe Aſperſions, Slanders and Suggeſtions, which are late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly come abroad in the Nation cauſleſly upon them.</p>
            <q>
               <p>For among my People are found wicked men, that lie in wait, as he that ſets ſnares. They ſet a Trap, they catch them. As a Cage is full of Birds, ſo are their Houſes full of Deceit: Therefore they are become Great, and waxen Rich.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Jer. 5.26, 27.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed in the Year, 1665.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:49253:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:49253:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The <hi>REMONSTRANCE</hi> of the Suffering-People of God, called QUAKERS; clearing their Innocency from the many falſe Asperſions, Slan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and Suggeſtions, which are lately come abroad in the Nation (cauſleſly) upon them.</head>
            <p>FOraſmuch as the everlaſting God of all Truth hath vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſited us from on high, out of his Everlaſting Love un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us, and hath revealed Jeſus Chriſt, the Light of the world and the Life of men, unto us and in us; who have waited and longed for his appearance unto our ſouls, that we might be partakers of his Heavenly Power from on high; and that we might know his Eternal Power made ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt to us, and in us, by which the Saints in former ages were led and guided into all Truth, and to walk in the ſame to the honour of God, the Everlaſting Being, from whom Eternal Life is conveyed, through Chriſt Jeſus, unto all that do believe in the meaſure of his Eternal Spirit, which he hath given to every one a meaſure of to profit withal, even every man that is come into the world, to that intent and end that every one who receiveth it, and cloſeth with it in their hearts, might be led from darkneſs unto Light, from ſin unto Righteouſneſs, from Satan's power to the Power of God; and from death, and him that hath the power of death which is the Devil, unto God, the Everlaſting God of all Truth; and to have fellowſhip with him in the myſtery of the Goſpel of his Son <hi>Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> by which remiſſion of ſin is obtained, and an inheritance among the Sanctified Ones, who were made meet to be partakers thereof, who are gone before, and reſt in the boſom of the Father; unto which high and great Calling God hath called us, even to be partakers of the ſame Faith, Hope, Inheritance and Calling, through the riches of his Love, manifeſt to us in <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> in the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:49253:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>end of the world. Now, and in the laſt times, that hath yet been in being, or ever appeared amongſt the ſons of men, a neceſſity is laid upon us on the Lord's behalf, in whom we have believed, to ſpeak the truth <hi>as it is in Jeſus,</hi> before God and all his holy Angels, and before all men, and to the Witneſs of God in every man in the world, who yet doth not believe; yet according to this in all Conſciences will his Judgment be, and unto that everlaſting Teſtimony of God in all <hi>Engliſh-hearted-men,</hi> and all men of every Nation, Kindred, Tongue and People upon the face of the whole Earth; and to the Teſtimony in all Conſciences who live and have a being, according to Gods everlaſting Witneſs in them, we appeal, and that ſhall bear witneſs to us; that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther before, now, or hereafter, that we have, do, and ſhall ſpeak the truth as it is in Jeſus Chriſt, and according to which we muſt all be judged; and to receive Sentence from the hand of the Lord (according to what we ſhall declare unto all in this particular) for evermore.</p>
            <p>We are a People who have enquired after the Lord, and only deſired to know Him and his Worſhip, and that we might worſhip him in Spirit and in Truth, and find accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with him, and have fellowſhip with him in that which endures for evermore; that our ſouls might live in his ſight, and that we might witneſs his Countenance and Favour ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted to us; and the Evidence of his Spirit bearing wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to us, and in us, that we are accepted of him through Chriſt Jeſus. We are not ignorant of all the ſet and ſtinted Forms of Worſhip, and Formal profeſſion in our own gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and what it is, and what the enjoyments of all are in reſpect of God and his Worſhip; for we our ſelves have travelled thoſe paths in diligent circumſpection, and much vigilancy, in the obſervation of all thoſe outward things, which are accounted by ſome, as <hi>Divine and Holy Inſtitutions and Ordinances of God,</hi> which generally the People take upon truſt from their Leaders and Elders, Tradition of time, or Cuſtom of Nations; but alas, we know how it was with us in that ſtate, and how it is with all ſuch, who are ſo buſying themſelves about bodily exerciſes, which profit little, while their hearts are not upright to that of God made manifeſt in
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:49253:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>them, by which he ſhews unto man his thoughts and his evil, and alſo that which is good and acceptable in his ſight; yet notwithſtanding all ſuch who are profeſſing God and Chriſt in words and worſhip, and yet be enemies to him, and that which may be known of him in their hearts, both in life and works: And ſuch were we in times paſt, in ignorance and unbelief, and yet had a profeſſion, and a zeal according to the times, but not according to the true knowledge of God in Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
            <p>But God out of his rich Love and Mercy had compaſſion on us in this eſtate, and knew the longing and thirſting of our hearts after him that we might obtain him, manifeſted his Eternal Words of Life and Power in our hearts, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a Light unto our feet, and a Lanthorn unto our paths, by which we came to ſee our ſelves and our own eſtate, and that all our righteouſneſs were as filthy rags; and that all the inventions, traditions and ordinances of men, which are repugnant unto the Will and Ordinances of Chriſt, that all theſe were and are abomination unto the Lord, and that he hath no pleaſure in them; neither in them that draw near unto him, pretending honour and worſhip unto him, while they offer up unto him in the darkneſs and ignorance of their minds, with polluted hearts and lips, and that which he never required. Theſe things are an Abomination, we being made ſenſible thereof by the Spirit of God, which diſcovers both words and works; and knowing his Judgment to come upon us, not only for ſin, but alſo for that which hath been, and is by ſome yet counted for righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs and worſhip, who are ſtill in the unbelief; the Lord made a ſeparation in our hearts betwixt the <hi>Precious</hi> and the <hi>Vile,</hi> and called us out of the <hi>unfruitful works of darkneſs,</hi> and out of the <hi>World,</hi> and its wiſdom which knows not God, and out of the paths of thoſe who are in the Fall, and in the Apoſtacy, and are erred from the Life and Power of God, and the holy Injunctions of Chriſt, not to have any more fellowſhip with them in the vain corrupt traditions of men, nor them that would ſet mans threſhold by God's threſhold; and not only ſo, but would even overthrow both the Life,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:49253:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>Power and Vertue of all true Religion and holy Exerciſe, to ſet up the Conſtitutions and Decrees of man, and Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Imaginations of men, in a bodily ſhew of holy Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, when God requires no ſuch thing of man; moreover, would impoſe the fallible Judgments and changeable Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions of men, upon mens Conſciences, and would be Lords over mens Faith: ſuch we cannot own, neither have fellowſhip with, but are clearly ſeparated from ſuch things in our hearts, and cannot own ſuch with the preſence of our perſons, in conformity to that which we ſee no ground for, neither themſelves can give any, out of the Scriptures of Truth, or from the Examples of the Apoſtles, and primitive Church, ſo called. For this thing we have been railed and ſlandred, miſreported, defamed and evil-ſpoken of, falſly accuſed, evilly entreated, reproached, mocked, ſtocked, ſtoned, impriſoned, whipped, buffeted, our Goods ſpoiled, and our Families ſought to be ruined, and we not counted worthy to live in our Country and Land of our Nativity: Therefore Devices have been made, and Engines formed againſt us, and Laws and Acts made that we muſt either con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form to that which no man as yet hath convinced us of, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by diſcourſe, word or writing, or elſe we cannot enjoy our Liberties, as men, in the Nation; but muſt be baniſhed, as perſons unfit to live among men, or in our natural habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, ſeparated from our Wives and dear Children, in jeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pardy of our Lives if we return in ſeven years; nay, in peril daily, in loſs of Goods, Mulcts, Fines, long Impriſonments; and he that doth the moſt miſchief unto us, thinks he doth God the moſt ſervice, and the Kingdom the beſt office.</p>
            <p>But as the enemy of mankind, the Devil and Satan, ceaſeth not to repreſent the beſt of the Lords works in a bad form; even ſo doth his Inſtruments, the Lords People; and of their life and works to ſtir up a diſlike in Peoples minds againſt them, and therefore the greateſt <hi>Truth</hi> by ſome hath been counted the greateſt <hi>Hereſy.</hi> The <hi>Jews,</hi> the alone Church of God in that age, all the <hi>Gentiles</hi> hated, and the Nations that knew not God, whom God reproved: Chriſt the Prince of Peace, was ſaid to be a <hi>Samaritan,</hi> and to <hi>have a Devil,</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:49253:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>and to <hi>caſt out Devils by Beelzabub the Prines of Devils,</hi> and to be <hi>an Enemy to Caeſar,</hi> and <hi>a Friend of Publicans and Sinners,</hi> and <hi>a Blaſphemer,</hi> and <hi>a Breaker of the Law of Moſes,</hi> and <hi>a Tranſgreſſor of the Ordinances of the Jews,</hi> and what not? <hi>He was numbered amongst Tranſgreſſors,</hi> and <hi>a Murderer preferred before him;</hi> and he that was given for the <hi>Light of the Gentiles,</hi> and <hi>the Salvation of Iſrael,</hi> and of all, to the ends of the Earth, was counted as the <hi>Troubler</hi> and <hi>Diſturber</hi> of their State and Government: And ſo it happened to all his Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers, and the Prophets that went before; <hi>Elias</hi> was reckoned by <hi>Ahab,</hi> his <hi>Enemy,</hi> and <hi>the Troubler of Iſrael;</hi> and likewiſe, <hi>Micah</hi> and <hi>Jeremiah</hi> were reckoneo as men fallen away to the forreign Enemies, <hi>viz.</hi> to the <hi>Babylonians</hi> in the the time of <hi>Zedekiah;</hi> becauſe he pleaſed not the Princes of <hi>Zedekiah,</hi> they put him in the Dungeon, his feet ſtuck faſt in the mire: <hi>Iſaiah</hi> was counted <hi>a Troubler of the People,</hi> and <hi>a Diſturber of Jeruſalem</hi> and the Country, ſo that they, ſaid, <hi>Speak no more of theſe things unto us, for we will not hear them.</hi> What ſhould I ſpeak of <hi>Paul,</hi> of <hi>Peter,</hi> of <hi>James,</hi> of <hi>Stephen,</hi> of <hi>Silas,</hi> of <hi>John</hi> and of all the Holy Men of God, of <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> of all the Believers among the <hi>Jews,</hi> of all the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers among the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and of the ſuffering Brethren in the Apoſtles dayes, and of all the ſuffering Chriſtians by the <hi>Romans,</hi> and in the ten Perſecutions in latter years in <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope,</hi> where the Name of Chriſt was publiſhed? ſo that the beſt of men have been in all ages reckoned by the Powers of the world and People thereof, the greateſt Malefactors, and have been counted, not worthy to live; but Enemies to States and Governments, Turners of the world upſide down, Seditious, Peſtilent, deſperate, Wicked, Ringleaders of Sects, Setters out of ſtrange gods, Deceivers, Deluders, Deſpiſers of Princes, Enemies to Churches, States, to Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Wealths, and Enemies to all mankind, Diſturbers of Reace, of Misbehaviout, and what not? In a word, not one of the faithful People of God, in any age or generation, but they were condemned, and cenſured, as Evil-doers, and were made to ſuffer as ſuch, the moſt, by ſome publick pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Law, or (if I may ſay) perverted Law, or other,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:49253:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>whereby they were judged; or elſe by making ſome Law or other to ſuit their intended purpoſe, to be a cloak and a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver unto them of ſome ſhew and ſeeming Reaſon why they ſo proceed, in a ſeeming way of legality, to blind the minds of People; that it was done by the force of ſome Equitable Power, and that all that were Tranſgreſſors of ſuch Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances and Laws, though never ſo repugnant to the mind of God, yet all ought to obey them: And they that ſuffered by them were reckoned as Evil-doers; And ſo all the Saints have ſuffered, and were condemned by the world: But Chriſt is come for this very end, to convince the world of Sin, of Righteouſneſs, and of Judgment, and will condemn that Judgment which is acted by the power of the Prince of this world, becauſe he ſhall be caſt out, and muſt not for ever ſit as Judge over the Heritage of God; for then the Lord's Heritage would be laid waſte, and the Deſtroyer and his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments trumph in their wicked enterprizes.</p>
            <p>We who are brought forth in this laſt age of the world, and have been made to tremble becauſe of the Word of the Lord, and the dread of his Holineſs; that we have ſeen and known, called reproachfully <hi>Quakers;</hi> We have been a ſuffering People, ſince the Lord hath called us, and choſen us out of the world, to bear witneſs to his Name, and to that everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Truth, by which freedom from Sin is witneſſed; which the Prophets and Holy Men of God of old, the Apoſtles, and Members of the Church of Chriſt were made Teſtators of; and we are Members of the ſame Body, and do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve no other things than that which all the Prophets bare witneſs unto, and all the Apoſtles and Miniſters of Chriſt, and Members of the Church of Chriſt, which is his Body; believed, and no other Hope or Faith have we, or profeſs we, than that which was once delivered unto the Saints of old, in the pure and holy Plantation of the Goſpel; nor no other belief have we, either as to Doctrine or Practice, but that which is conſiſtent with the Church of Chriſt, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Scriptures of Truth: And though we have had greas oppoſition, yet hath none convinced us of Errour, or of Evil-doing in point of practice, as walking in the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieties
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:49253:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>of men; but we have endeavoured with great dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, to <hi>make our Calling and Election ſure,</hi> and that we might have a <hi>Conſcience void of offence towards God, and</hi> alſo <hi>towards</hi> all <hi>men,</hi> and to <hi>ſerve the Lord in our generation,</hi> and to <hi>do good unto all men,</hi> as much as in us lies; and to ſtudy Peace and Quietneſs, minding every one our particular Calling whereunto God hath called us, that we might adorn the Goſpel of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, by a holy and blameleſs Converlation, by which we have received remiſſion of Sins, and are remitted unto God; yet notwithſtanding, great hath been the enmity that hath been raiſed up againſt us, and great hath been the out-cryes of many, and much the hatred; though we can ſay, in a clear Conſcience, with <hi>David, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a cauſe:</hi> And great have been our Sufferings this many years, inſomuch, as we may ſay truly, <hi>Long Furrows have been plowed upon our backs, and we have had all manner of Evil ſpoken of us;</hi> but we bleſs and magnify the Lord, <hi>not for evil doing,</hi> but falſly, yea falſly, for the Name ſake of Chriſt; though we have been ſlanderouſly, and faſly reported from time to time, by the the Time-ſerving-Miniſters of Antichriſt, who have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes<note n="*" place="margin">Witneſs that their Addreſs to <hi>Richard,</hi> called Protector.</note> flattered the Powers of the world, and ſtirred them up againſt us, by falſe ſuggeſtions, flatterings, and daubing inſinuations, becauſe we have diſcovered their Deceit, and our Converſation hath been more blameleſs than theirs; they have prevailed ſo far, as to raiſe up unbelief in peoples hearts, and to ſet the Rulers of the Earth againſt us, as much as in them lay, to our utter ruine and extirpation in this life, as ever <hi>Haman</hi> did againſt the <hi>Jews:</hi> But ſeeing the adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary of mankind hath prevailed ſo far with many, to hear, receive and believe the many falſe ſlanderous reports of us, and to publiſh them abroad; and ſeeing that traps are laid for us, and ſnares for our feet, both to enſnare our Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, and to the ruine of our Eſtates, to bring us into bonds, to the ſeparating us from our Wives and Children, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſcation of our Eſtates, to <hi>Baniſhment</hi> of us our of our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ive Country to ſeek our bread among ſtrangers, to the ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:49253:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>of us odious unto all, to the making of us Slaves and Bond-men, and ſell us to any <hi>for a thing of nought;</hi> to make People believe we are not ſubject unto Authority, that we diſobey the Laws of the Nation, which are juſt; that we plot Miſchief againſt the Government; that we are ready to ſide with a Forreign Enemy, to bring the Nation again into a Civil War; that we hold correſpondency with Forreign Enemies; that we annimate one another in Sedition, and Rebellion; and that the principal end of all our Meetings and Conventicles, ſo called, is, to confirm one another in Malice againſt the Government; And that we make Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lections for the ſupport of a Party, who are liſted to appear in any deſperate undertaking; That we have deſigned the very time; That we are induſtrious, and dextrous, and ſpread abroad our intelligence to ſtir us Strife and Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and to diſturb the publick Peace of the Nation: And this greatly reflects upon us, and not only upon us, but the everlaſting Truth of Chriſt Jeſus, which we profeſs, which if theſe things were true, we were not fit to live in a Nation, but to ſuffer according to our demerits. And ſeeing two Acts are chiefly made againſt us, for the ſuppreſſing of our Innocent and Peaceable Meetings, whereby diverſe thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands are, and have been, and are like to be in bonds, only (we ſay) for the Worſhip of God; and keeping Faith and a good Conſcience; yet how great ſeverity hath been uſed againſt us, God knows, and many good People in the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion alſo! Notwithſtanding, as though this had not been enough yet, our Sufferings are augmented, and Affliction unto Affliction, by a Letter lately ſent by ſome Chief Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate of <hi>England</hi> (as we are enformed) to the Nobility and Juſtices of the ſeveral Counties, which is read in ſome places in the publick Seſſions; in which, though we be not particularly nominated in that Letter, yet many of thoſe things contained in it, are imputed unto us; and the Juſtices of Peace, and others, take it for granted: And ſo our Miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, Bonds and Sufferings are augmented time after time; which, if the Lord by his eternal Power doth not change the minds of them that are bent againſt us, we are like to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:49253:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>as men from having a being amongſt the reſt of our Neighbours and Country-men.</p>
            <p>Therefore, all theſe things conſidered, We are neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated to declare our Innocency unto all, and to clear the truth of ſuch things wherein ſome are jealous of us, and to ſpeak the truth from our hearts and Conſciences, as before the Living God, the Judge of the quick and the dead, who in his day will render unto every one according to his works; and alſo before his holy Angels, and all juſt men; and to all the Potentates, Nobility, Rulers, Magiſtrates, Juſtices of Peace, and to all People in this Nation; and to all the whole World; and to every particular Perſon where this may come: and according to the truth of this our Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, we deſire the Lord may judge us; and we never to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect his Bleſſing upon us if we do it not with all ſincerity of heart, and uprightneſs before him.</p>
            <p>Firſt of all, We cannot but teſtify unto all with boldneſs, That we love the King's perſon, and deſire his good in that which pertains to this life, and that which is to come, and that his Throne may be eſtabliſhed in Righteouſneſs, that we under him may live a Godly, Honeſt and Peaceable life, ſerving God in our generation, and doing that which is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable in his ſight, and that which becomes true Members of this Kingdom, that it might be preſerved in Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Peace.</p>
            <p n="2">2. We utterly deny all ſuch, as not to be of us, and did never, neither can, nor ſhall ever own ſuch to be of us, who plot or contrive any Sedition, Rebellion, Inſurrection or Miſdemeanor againſt the Peace of the Nation, to embroil it again into Wars; we utterly do deny all ſuch things from our hearts, and alſo every individual perſon that hath, doth, or may act any thing conducing to ſuch a miſchievous end; and deny all deſperate perſons and their deſigns, who wiſh or deny all deſperate perſons and their deſigns, who wiſh or deſire in their hearts evil to the King, or to any of his Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, or that act any thing conducing unto War for the hurt of the Nation in general, or any particular men therein.</p>
            <p n="3">3. We utterly deny all ſuch Councils, whether few or many, and their confederacies, who hold any correſpondency with any forreign Enemy or domeſtick, if any ſuch there are, have
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:49253:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>been, or ſhall be; and likewiſe any ſuch Order as any perſon or perſons ſhall ſend abroad in any part of the Nation, to the diſquieting or diſturbing the Peace of the Nation, as is mentioned in that Letter.</p>
            <p n="4">4. We utterly deny ſuch as have provided any Arms, or liſted any men, (if any ſuch there be) to aid or aſſiſt any For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Enemy, or to breed any Contention at home in the Nation; and have not fellowſhip with ſuch unprofitable works of darkneſs, but do utterly deny them, and all ſuch contrivances.</p>
            <p n="5">5. We deny all ſuch as by any falſe inſinuation or ſugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions alienate the minds of any of the People from their du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to their Prince or Nation; but rather do exhort all men, <hi>To ſtudy Peace, to be quiet, and ceaſe from Strife and Contention; and to ſtop their ears from hearing, or receiving that which tends to the hurt of the Nation, or any particular man therein.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. We are not ſo void of reaſon and underſtanding, but that we know and are ſenſible that any forreign Nation, or People, who are Aliens unto another People, if at any time they ſhould prevail in way of War or Hoſtility upon any Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or part thereof, we know it would imbondage the whole, and make all greater ſufferers, as experience doth daily teach; therefore knowing and being ſenſible of ſuch things, we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but judge and condemn all ſuch deſires in any, much more their actions, if any ſhould attempt any ſuch things in the diſcontent of their minds, to be fooliſh, treacherous and inhumane; and whoſoever are actors in any ſuch things, we utterly diſown them to be ſo far void of truth, that they have loſt their underſtandings as men.</p>
            <p n="7">7. And all ſuch Meetings, or Conventicles, which are Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditious and Unlawfull in the ſight of God, we deny; whoſe principal end is to confirm each other in Malice againſt the Government; or do make any Collections to ſupport any Party, or raiſe any moneys for any liſted men, who appear in any deſperate undertaking, or any that have deſigned either time or place for any ſuch end, as to raiſe War; or to yeeld to any aid, either in our own Nation, or to any Party, if there be any ſuch, or to any Forreign Enemy; we do utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deny any ſuch, both their perſons and practiſes.</p>
            <p n="8">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:49253:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
8. But we freely confeſs unto all, and before all, we have met together this many years for the Worſhip of God, to pray together in the holy Ghoſt, to exhort one another unto Righteouſneſs, and to build up one another in the moſt holy Faith, as the Chriſtians of old did, and dare not forſake the aſſembling of our ſelves together unto this innocent and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly duty, that God requires all Chriſtian men to be exerciſed in; neither do we limit the Lord to time or place, as ſome do, and would have us to conform to that which we are not perſwaded of in our hearts, neither are we convinced of by any, but rather confirmed by the Scriptures of Truth, and by our daily witneſſing of Gods Preſence amongſt us: Although we are liable to many ſufferings therfore, and have undergone great penalties meetly for the Worſhip of God, for which end we ever met, and no other, as God knows, and all that have been preſent at our Aſſemblies from time to time can bear witneſs, who are not of us, nor of our perſwaſion, either as to doctrine or practice in many particulars: Yet we freely confeſs before God and all men, we have had Collections amongſt us, God having put it into our hearts, that of what we have, and what God hath bleſſed us with, we have been, and ſtill are, out of our ſmall eſtates ready to maintain good works; for it's Chriſt and the Apoſtles Doctrine: <hi>For if we ſay we love God, and ſuffer our Brother to want, how then dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the Love of God in us?</hi> Beſides, we have many poor Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows and Fatherleſs, and many poor Priſoners, who are ſufferers for Chriſt and the Goſpels ſake, unto whom we have miniſtred without being chargeable unto any Pariſh in the Nation for our Poor; beſides the Contribution for the Poor of the ſeveral Pariſhes in the Nation, and other good and neceſſary works we have maintained, and ſhall be ready while we enjoy any thing in this preſent world: Beſides theſe works of Charity, God he knows, and we are bold to chalenge all the whole World to prove, that ever we collected any thing but for the aforeſaid vertuous and pious uſes, according to the will of God.</p>
            <p n="9">9. We deny all ſuch, if any ſuch there be, who make any ſuch Collections in their Aſſemblies to maintain War, or to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:49253:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>buy any Weapons of War, and to encourage or ſupport any ſuch deſperate undertaking, to carry on any deſign under any pretence whatſoever, againſt the Peace of the Kingdom or Government of the ſame, or to the diſturbing or hurting of any man, or men, either in perſon or eſtate.</p>
            <p n="10">10. We our ſelves know that <hi>Sion</hi> muſt not be builded with Blood, nor the Church of God by Weapons of War, nor Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion propagated by Violence; and therefore we cannot ſtrive with thoſe Weapons, nor with any Carnal Weapons of War, either fight to defend or offend, being redeemed out of thoſe things; and can forgive our enemies, and bleſs them that curſe us, and pray for them that perſecute us, and do good to them that evil intreat us; and have learned the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Chriſt, knowing if any do us wrong or injuſtice, <hi>Vengeance belongs to the Lord,</hi> and he hath wayes enow to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence them, ſo that we need not, neither are we careful in this matter, but have committed our ſelves unto the Lord, the faithful Creator and Preſerver of all that do believe; and we cannot render evil for evil, nor ſeek revenge, nor reviling for reviling; Yet knowing the Innocency of our own hearts, and that the glorious Truth of our God is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned with us, we cannot but deny all falſe ſlanders and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſations that have been laid to our charge, and ſpeak the Truth, and teſtifie it before all, and unto all, that it may be believed, and Truth cleared before all.</p>
            <p n="11">11. Whoever they be that have, do, or ſhall hereafter plot, contrive, conſult, levy War, raiſe Arms, joyn with any for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign or domeſtick Enemies, under any pretence whatſoever, againſt the King or Government, or to the diſturbing of the Nation, or to bring it into any commotion, in any hoſtile way or manner, We in the preſence of the Lord, and before all men in the Nation do deny from our ſincere hearts all ſuch, and their practices, as to be out of the Truth of the Goſpel, and we have not, nor cannot have any fellowſhip with them: Therefore let none impute any ſuch things un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us, or trouble us any more with their groundleſs jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, ſurmiſes, or charges of this nature, which we are inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent in. And O that the inmoſt part of all our heart were
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:49253:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>open and bare before all in Authority in the Nation! And, O that you had no greater enemies at home or abroad than we are! then might you all reſt in peace and quiet, without fear or jealouſie of any harming you.</p>
            <p>Laſt of all; Be it known unto all men We are reſolved in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Suffering-Principles, to <hi>bear all things, endure all things,</hi> and <hi>fuffer all things for Chriſts ſake;</hi> and if we muſt ſtill ſuffer and undergo all thoſe hard and heavy cenſures which already are decreed and determined againſt us, Know all people it is for Chriſts ſake and the Goſpel, and for the Teſtimony of JESUS, and the Word and Worſhip of God, and not for evil-doings; and this we hope all good and tender-hearted people will believe and receive our Teſtimony, which will ballance the ſuggeſtions of our enemies; and we ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtly do believe the Lord will be with us in the midſt of all Tribulations, and will plead our Cauſe, and keep us from every evil way and work, and from the Temptations of the Adverſary, unto his heavenly Kingdom, that we ſhall not make ſhipwrack of Faith and a good Conſcience, nor faint in the midſt of Trials; and the Lord keep all men who thirſt after Righteouſneſs, from ſtriving againſt the Lord, or ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in oppoſition againſt his everlaſting Power, which who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever doth, cannot proſper; and though we be the only Mark and But to ſhoot at, and are reckoned as the off-ſcouring of all things, ſingled out from the reſt of the Nation as Abjects of Wrath, and Veſſels of Contempt, yet we knowing our own innocency, cannot betray it, but ſuffer in Faith and Patience, and travel in hope to ſee an end of all ſufferings, and bear the reproach for Chriſt's ſake, till he ariſe in his Power and Glory, and make his enemies his footſtool. And indeed we cannot but pitty and commiſerate their ſtate who yet are in oppoſition to us, that they ſhould thus requite the Lord for all his kindneſs after their deliverance out of their adverſity, trouble and afflictions, as to make it the main matter of concernment in the Nation to root out and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the Flock of Chriſt, whom he hath redeemed to himſelf as a <hi>purchaſed Poſſeſſion,</hi> and think by this means to ſettle all in reſt and peace. Oh the Lord open all their eyes that ſo
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:49253:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>judge; for they know not what they are doing, neither how ill the Lord takes it at their hands, that inſtead of encouraging, cheriſhing and being as a ſafeguard and refuge, they only ſhould diſcourage and make ſad the hearts of many poor and innocent people, whom God never made ſad, and ſhould add affliction unto affliction; and that the glorious Truth of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> which hath been ſo richly made manifeſt both in word and operation, to the changing of thouſands from ſin and ungodlineſs, to bear the image of God, and bring forth fruits of Righteouſneſs, and ſeaſon the Earth, that the Nation might be bleſſed with the dew from above, and with the heavenly and ſpiritual bleſſing in <hi>Chriſt-Jeſus.</hi> But O how is all this ſlighted in the Nation! and O how doth Vice abound, and Wickedneſs and Ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs encreaſe! and how do men run after it as if it were the way to felicity and happineſs! O what prophaneſs is broken-forth like a land-flood over all the banks! what horrible Oaths and Blaſphemy, what prodigious Swearing and Curſing, as if it were even daring God to damn them; nay, ſome do frequently uſe thoſe very words of daring God to it, and ſaying, <hi>[God confound them]</hi> is the frequent wicked ſpeeches of many in the Nation, and taking God's Name in vain at every trivial occaſion; and O what drunkenneſs and filthy uncleanneſs, not fit to be named among men! what ſwearing and forſwearing! that it may truly be ſaid, <hi>Becauſe of Oaths,</hi> as of old, <hi>the Land mourns:</hi> and what ſports, vain-paſtimes, that begets people into lightneſs and wantonneſs, are permitted, if not allowed! which are bad and wicked fruits, and demonſtrate the fear of God to be far away from them, that act and countenance ſuch things, as people running on heaps unto ſuch vanities: but to meet in the fear of God, and for the worſhip of God, or for holy Exerciſes, this is reckoned <hi>Sedition,</hi> and counted dangerous and deſtructive to the Peace of the Nation; and nothing but Perſecution and Cruelty attends ſuch; which if it be continued and perſiſted in, will bring a ſcourge of God upon the Nation. Therefore once more be warned; <hi>Break off theſe bonds of wickedneſs, and ceaſe from perſecuting of God's People, and repent while you have time, if you can find a place, Leſt the fire of the Lords Jealouſie ſmoak againſt you, and there be none able to quench it, or deliver you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By the ſuffering and afflicted People of God, who are perſecuted for Christs ſake, called</hi> QUAKERS.</p>
            <p>It is the ſame Faith and Hope that we hold, and not another, for which the Apoſtles of Chriſt ſuffered, and were perſecuted: yet there is none will ſay in our generation, that the Apoſtles did evil; nor none ſay, that they did well that perſecuted them. Therefore conſider of it, you that are doing the ſame thing you condemn in others.</p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:49253:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
